<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
              <title type="part"></title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <respStmt>
              <persName role="publisher">Niels Pfeffer</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <date>2019</date>
          </publicationStmt>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
        <p>
          [The student plays:]
        </p>
        <notatedMusic>
          <ptr target="beginning1.mei" />
        </notatedMusic>

        <p>
          <foreign xml:lang="de">Mein persönlicher Geschmack geht dahin, etwas mehr auf die drei zu
          spielen, sodass ein trochäischer Rhythmus — ◡ entsteht. Es gibt
          zwar kaum Situationen, in denen etwas wichtiges auf der 3 vorkommt.
          Aber auf der anderen Seite ändert sich die Figur selbst eben auf der
          dritten Zählzeit.</foreign>
        </p>

        <p>
          I think that in the beginning and in places that are like the beginning,
          you should think of the right hand as the main hand and not as somehow
          a harmonic accompaniment of the left hand. So I would change register
          more in the right hand from the first beat to the third beat so that it
          has more of a shape. Right now it is just an accompaniment. Something
          like that:
        </p>

        <notatedMusic>
          <ptr target="beginning2.mei" />
        </notatedMusic>

        <p>
          And then a real contrast in the middle section, when you have the other
          figuration – maybe even on the upper manual, so that it sounds like a concerto
          structure.
        </p>

        <p>
          If you are thinking of the upper part as more somehow representing what
          an orchestra would do and the actual figuration that is written is more
          a kind of, you could say textual embellishment of a transcription of an
          orchestral concerto, why don’t we take that idea one step further?
        </p>

        <notatedMusic>
          <ptr target="beginning3.mei"></ptr>
        </notatedMusic>

        <p>
          And then in bar 14 actually all three are accented, but they aren’t equal.
        </p>

        <notatedMusic>
          <ptr target="middle-section1.mei"></ptr>
        </notatedMusic>

        <p>
          And then something more like a two-voice texture.
        </p>

        <notatedMusic>
          <ptr target="middle-section2.mei"></ptr>
        </notatedMusic>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
