<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe Zwölftes Probstück (english translation)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Niels Pfeffer</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Mattheson.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations</head>
      <div n="1" type="section">
        <head>§. 1.</head>
        <p xml:id="p1-1">
          If there is something difficult in this work of the <hi rendition="#i">Organisten-Probe</hi>,
          I will have to admit that it could be the fifteenth example of the middle class and
          this twelfth of the upper class.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="section">
        <head>§. 2.</head>
        <p xml:id="p2-1">
          Most of the present example's difficulty lies without doubt in the unfamiliar or
          supposedly unfamiliar clefs: because of that the high F and the high alto clef have
          been chosen on porpuse in order that a diligent player will become even more experienced in those
          allegedly uncommon keys and clefs.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3" type="section">
        <head>§. 3.</head>
        <p xml:id="p3-1">
          The best warning that can be given to good friends in the present occasion is primarily
          that they take care of certain leaps, of which there are many in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000002132490626">first</ref>,
          <ref target="#measure-0000000440142618">third</ref>,
          <ref target="#measure-0000001403554075">fourth</ref> and
          <ref target="#measure-0000000306381863">fifth measure</ref> etc.,
          for they are not common octaves as they occur daily and a lot of times but
          they are slightly further apart as you find them often on gambas.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4" type="section">
        <head>§. 4.</head>
        <p xml:id="p4-1">
          Secondly I point to the <ref target="#measure-0000001831952514">beginning of the second part</ref>
          of this test piece and imploringly ask you to take care and to ignore everything else.
          Only seconds are written above the notes, nothing more. An apprentice that moved up
          from the middle class to the upper class has to know himself if the implicated fourth
          needs to be major or minor according to the nature and quality of the harmony and of the key
          to which it belongs. If regarding the melody the key does change, the required figures are
          usually clearly written above and where they are not written above they can be left away
          quite rightly since the player needs to know the characteristics and nature of the key,
          which is the only thing we are looking for here.
          Between ourselves I want to enlighten that to the
          <ref target="#note-0000000910720915">fifth note in the second measure </ref>
          of the mentioned second section belongs the major fourt (4+) in order to avoid a
          so-called false-relation in voice leading, which would arise between plain g
          and the g flat.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="5" type="section">
        <head>§. 5.</head>
        <p xml:id="p5-1">
          Even though <ref target="#fb-1">a sixth</ref> is written above the
          <ref target="#note-0000000305001791">last note of the third crotchet</ref>
          in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000699331102">fifth measure of the second section</ref>
          one cannot conclude, that it is played at precisely that place, but
          context and elagance require this sixth to be played on the previous note.
          This anticipation has been mentioned previously already, but is to be assumed
          that one does not like to go back so far in order look for the remark and
          its cause. In the different places of the same sort in this test piece it is the same case.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="6" type="section">
        <head>§. 6.</head>
        <p xml:id="p6-2">
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000904640872">seventh measure of the last section</ref>
          an invention is found that is developed for some measures and,
          after an interluding alternation of little secondary motives, comes in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001474684480">fourteenth measure</ref>. In those
          sequences and jumps it should be noted that they do not require any more
          art than playing on each crotchet a single chord given either by the nature
          and characteristics of the key or by the figures. This means, that this single
          chord is played always on the first note of every crotchet and not on any
          of the three following notes.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="7" type="section">
        <head>§. 7.</head>
        <p xml:id="p7-1">
          For the reasons already given in the fourth paragraph, one shall notice
          the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001586855072">eleventh measure of the second section</ref>
          of this test piece and the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001984106098">22nd</ref> and
          <ref target="#measure-0000000443751460">23rd measure</ref> of the same section too,
          so that everything is accurate regarding the written figures. Especially in a test one
          shall choose to take care for the third measure before the end and if there is
          no hasitating and stumbling, the player shall be praised. Presumably on the first
          note of the mentioned measure there will be some hesitation, I know it from experience.
          But everything is put so naturally and in a way that once the reasonables are told how
          it is like they understand it easily and right away. If only some will confess that they
          did not get it right and understood it quite differently.
          Nothing is prescribed here to those who know it and who are able to.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="8" type="section">
        <head>§. 8.</head>
        <p xml:id="p8-1">
          Although this key is seldomly the root of a piece or of an aria (yet there is no
          lack of printed examples as we saw in the respective place in the middle class),
          pieces in F minor modulate often into their third scale degree, bA:
          That is, why a thorough-bass player necessarily has to be well-versed in this
          key as well, even if it is not the piece's tonality but only a related key.
          One shall study and look once more at the aria of Marcello on p. 356, which will
          prove the correctness of the said.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="9" type="section">
        <head>§. 9.</head>
        <p xml:id="p9-1">
          Yet what do talk so much of F minor? The daily and common <hi rendition="#b">C minor</hi>
          modulates often into <hi rendition="#b">bA</hi>, its natural sixth. To prove that can serve,
          among thousands of other things, a particular cantata of the <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118544489">Capell-Meister
          <hi rendition="#b">Ha&#x0364;ndel</hi></persName>, which is not printed but in many people's hands and which
          is well-known. It is called <name type="musicalWork" ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/300064926"><hi rendition="#b">Lucretia</hi></name> and its first words
          <hi rendition="#aq">O Numi eterni &amp;c.</hi>, from which will likely know it. The second aria of
          this cantata has, immediately at the beginning of the B section, the following
          modulation:
        </p>
        <notatedMusic xml:id="music-example1">
          <ptr target="music-example1.xml" />
        </notatedMusic>
      </div>

      <div n="10" type="section">
        <head>§. 10.</head>
        <p xml:id="p10-1">
          Those few notes of an aria in <hi rendition="#b">C minor</hi> include the
          <hi rendition="#b">G Sharp</hi> or <hi rendition="#b">A flat</hi> and one who does not know and
          practises them as their own tonalities will not be able to play the given
          one and a half lines correctly. By now there are more examples of this kind
          than one may count.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="11" type="section">
        <head>§. 11.</head>
        <p xml:id="p11-1">
          We need to say a word about the use of the sixth and fourth, since for
          some non-greeks it might seem shocking. This is it: that when an eager legalist
          finds the sixth and the fourth now and then in somewhat exceptional places and
          not according to the old way, he will be asked for the goodness to ascribe a
          good intention to it, which primarily aims to make the student more experienced
          steady. Someone who wants to do well in horsemanship is known to get on
          a wild and unordered horse from time to time, too. The same here. I could have
          changed it easily and proceed more legally than the oldest counterpointist of the
          spartanic school. yet the legality of Emerepes counts by far not as much as the
          one of Iustitian: which also tolerates things falling away or being added.
          Regarding the sixth and the fourth I am almost devoted to the opinion of
          Aristoxenes which is still accepted and exercised among the greeks and I have
          because of the combination with the sixth a special esteem for the poor fourth
          so that I do not completly estimate it equal to all the other dissonances
          but sometimes I allow it a safe conduct.
        </p>
      </div>

    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
