<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe zweites Probstück (english translation)</title>
        <editor role="translator">
          <persName xml:id="pfeffer">
            <surname>Pfeffer</surname>
            <forename>Niels</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <persName>
            <surname>Pfeffer</surname>
            <forename>Niels</forename>
          </persName>
        </publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
            <p>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations</head>
      <div n="1">
        <head>§. 1.</head>
        <p>
          This test piece can be used as a Toccata or at least like a good Toccatina.
          Already in the first measure the <ref target="#m-81">two quavers</ref>
          and their <ref target="#m-83">rests</ref> show
          that what the bass has already played before can be repeated in the treble.
          The <ref target="#m-87">second</ref>, <ref target="#m-226">fifth</ref>, <ref target="#m-377">eighth</ref>,
          <ref target="#m-729">16th</ref>,
          <ref target="#m-781">17th</ref>,
          <ref target="#m-841">18th</ref>,
          <ref target="#m-964">21st</ref> and <ref target="#m-1277">29th</ref> measure
          have the same meaning, and one only has to see what either precedes or
          succeeds in the bass, then one has found what the right hand can play,
          if one wants to be heard with it.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="2">
        <head>§. 2.</head>
        <p>
          Whenever there are passages
          such as in the <ref target="#m-192">fourth measure</ref>,
          one always goes along in leaps in the right hand according
          to the chord, starting from the third.
          In the <ref target="#m-269">sixth measure</ref> it should be noticed that
          arpeggio mentioned on p. 307
          <note type="editorial" resp="#pfeffer">
            See the annotations of Probstück 1, last example.
          </note>
          with sixths in the right hand, could be applied in the following way:

          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example1.xml" />
          </notatedMusic>
          This way of syncopating is very easy and makes a great effect, as if it was fair,
          which is why one can use it many times, with peculiar advantage and little effort.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3">
        <head>§. 3.</head>
        <p>
          There is a similar occasion in the <ref target="#m-433">ninth measure</ref>,
          where the same arpeggio can be used again.
          Where the <ref target="#discant-ref">low discant clef</ref> occurs and further on,
          <ref target="#m-1267">where the bass starts the same motive
          transposed to G</ref>, the process is the same.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4">
        <head>§. 4.</head>
        <p>
          <ref target="#m-635">At the beginning of the other part of this test piece,
          after the fermata 𝄐</ref>,
          one arpeggiates the chords and the figures placed above in a modest, or
          slow and staid manner, just with sixteenth notes, and proceeds
          for three measures that way. Should I reveal my opinion more clearly with notes?
          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example2.xml" />
          </notatedMusic>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="5">
        <head>§. 5.</head>
        <p xml:id="p5-1">
          Just as one mainly has to observe the already mentioned quavers for
          its placement of the main subject in the treble, it seems
          to be necessary to do a little reminder of that in the following 16th,
          17th and 18th measure. The motive appears three times:
          the first one begins on f, the other one immediately thereafter on b,
          and the third begins, when the bass has finished, on a g. For my terms,
          this can be said to be instructed clearly enough.

        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="6">
        <head>§. 6.</head>
        <p>
          As for the quavers in the <ref target="#m-1051">23nd</ref> to the
          <ref target="#m-1212">26th measure</ref>, it is easy to conclude that
          with such a colourful way of playing, one cannot be idle there.
          But there are innumerable variations and arpeggios to be mentioned,
          which all to record one would need a separate volume.
          If one wants to practise them in the present manner, the benefit can
          be great. For these exercises are not only colourful in themselves,
          but they contain general teachings which one must learn to apply to all
          kinds of different cases.
          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example3.xml" />
          </notatedMusic>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="7">
        <head>§. 7.</head>
        <p xml:id="p7-1">
          In the <ref target="#m-1382">last half of the 30th bar</ref>
          <note type="footnote" resp="#pfeffer">
            Mattheson probably meant measure 31.
          </note>
          the right hand can follow along in sixths;
          this is also the case in the
          <ref target="#m-1440">first half of the following 31st bar.</ref>
          <note type="footnote" resp="#pfeffer">
            32nd accordingly.
          </note>.

          The <ref target="#m-1459">last half of the same measure</ref> however
          is to be played in octaves in both hands and then alternates with
          sixths and octaves until the <ref target="#m-1609">three last measures</ref>
          which all can be played in octaves.

          I can already see in advance that some particularly old and stubborn
          ones will strongly shake about those octaves, for they think that this
          way of playing is completely against the etiquette.
          But they may think what they like, if they only believe, that I am concerned about nothing
          more than a good effect in playing and accompanying,
          and that I have not learned by mere contemplation, but from a long time of
          manual exercise,
          and that I experienced not through meditation but through long former
          exercise, how well such octaves fall into the ear, especially in powerful pieces.
          But I have also found that many who were unaccustomed to it,
          even though they were quite capable of playing the keyboard,
          it appeared Spanish to do the same thing in both hands, and they were stumbling
          quite a bit. I am inclined to say that it takes a great deal of practice
          to bring everything out cleanly in this way, with the quick notes.
          However, this type of playing is only suitable in certain places,
          and it must be done with great care.  Sometimes the basses of arias
          tolerate this quite well, sometimes not at all.
          But this can never be placed where a single voice is supposed to
          stand out, which a bright person can guess easily and
          take this test piece as an example.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="8">
        <head>§. 8.</head>
        <p>
          I have drafted this example quite conveniently on two little quarto leaves
          facing each other, not considering that it might take twice as much space
          in print and that it causes the hated trouble of turning pages in quick runs.
          Meanwhile, it is obvious that there was no other way to deal with the printed
          notes, since the demisemiquavers take up so much space below them,
          that sometimes just a half bar fits on a whole line.
          I lament the bulky shape of the notes a lot,
          since they do not only appear clumsily, but they also cause one to interrupt
          something that actually belongs together due to turning the page.
          This caused me to patch in a little in the end on p. 309
          <note type="footnote" resp="#pfeffer">
            m. 19.
          </note>
          by making <ref target="#m-914">a cadence</ref> and <ref target="#m-915">a rest</ref>
          that otherwise would not have come to my mind.
          A reasonable person will easily notice it and will excuse me.
          I did my best with it.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
