<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe dreiundzwanzigstes Probstück (english translation)</title>
        <editor role="translator">
          <persName xml:id="pfeffer">
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <persName>
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
            <p>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations</head>
      <div n="1" type="section">
        <head>§. 1.</head>
        <p>
          A soldier deserved to die, and the verdict was pronounced that he
          should jump off a high and steep cliff. As he now comes to the place,
          he takes a few steps backwards and takes a good run-up so that he can
          jump even better. But just as he reaches the edge, and everybody's eyes
          look for him in the bottom, he suddenly stops. This happens three times.
          Finally, the present general got angry and asked: Why is he hesitating?
          Why does he take three attempts and always stop on the edge? The brave
          soldier was not lazy, but replied to the general with great steadfastness:
          Monsieur, (for he was a Frenchman) you think that it is such a small
          thing to jump off this rock! It is true, I have tried it three times and
          I could not do it. I will gladly give you a fourth
          attempt, if you jump instead of me. Everyone, including the general himself,
          was amazed at this free answer, and the fellow was given his life.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="2" type="section">
        <head>§. 2.</head>
        <p>
          Now, some organists and their fellows may say: Dear God!
          Why is that written here? What comfort am I to draw from this story
          against the fear that this painful piece in C sharp brings to me?
          What explanation can the soldier give to me with his cheeky answer?
          Maybe, one compares this cheeky piece with it? No, my dear hero,
          it is not meant that way. I want to tell you how this story comes here,
          what comfort you have to get from its application and what explanation
          you can get from it.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3" type="section">
        <head>§. 3.</head>
        <p>
          First of all, if the piece is to be played
          <ref target="#tempo-001"><hi rendition="#aq">presto assai</hi></ref> and cleanly, it
          is not of the kind that can be brought out perfectly at once – such
          a jump takes more than a run-up. This way the story adds up.
          On the other hand, it is of great comfort to you, who is being tested,
          if I do not only say to you, like the soldier to the general, "I will
          give four attempts", but, "I will give you six and even
          more attempts". See, that is the comfort you get from my little story.
          Third, if you are given time to play the piece four or six times, it
          necessarily follows that practicing it will give you a great explanation.
          And there you have my answer.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4" type="section">
        <head>§. 4.</head>
        <p>
          Now do your best and let us hear you. I do not ask that the right hand
          should do the slightest thing except a few thirds every now and then.
          There will be no time for it, if the Presto assai should be taken care
          of.
          But beware of octaves and wrong chords at the highest velocity; otherwise
          one will hear them soon, no matter how you rush over it. It might be good
          if you play to him some measures, in particular the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000382832426 #measure-0000001511923609 #measure-0000001832895480 #measure-0000001416509068 #measure-0000001465555164 #measure-0000000450716618">
            six last ones</ref>,
          really slowly. Then you should be slightly ashamed.
          Now I do not see how to help you further and what else could also give
          you some guidance. This piece is so special that if I had not remembered
          this story, I could hardly have said a word to your advantage.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="5" type="section">
        <head>§. 5.</head>
        <p xml:id="p5-1">
          To the dear elderly who teach that the thorough-bass does not require
          such a velocity, that it is only stiff and does firma Spanish walks,
          I only want to leave the one thing and question for reflection:
          There are often words to sing that indicate a hurrying a running,
          a great restlessness, volatility and so on, but the human voice cannot
          always be used as desired because one cannot sing as quickly as one can
          play. I wonder whether the bass is not authorized to express the affect
          and the meaning of the text?
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
