<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe Erstes Probstück (english translation)</title>
        <editor role="translator">
          <persName xml:id="pfeffer">
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <persName>
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
            <p>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations</head>
      <div n="1" type="section">
        <head>§. 1.</head>
        <p xml:id="p1-1">
          The clergyman wished to compare the cheerless days of man's life with something and said
          they were like a musical book, in which commonly more black than white notes are to be found; his opinion was that
          similarly we encounter more misfortune than fortune in our lives. Whether or not the simile is lopsided, we will leave to rest.
          To me it appeared very ridiculous. For black notes imply a quick way of playing, signifying something cheerful rather than
          something sad. However, if the black color merely indicates an image of misery, one should rather choose a church or another assembly
          of the clergy, than a music book; since there are found more black than white clothes. I say it so that nobody thinks,
          he will be led into the school of fear and of the cross because of the slightly black notes in that class. Not at all, nobody
          may be afraid: for our notes are genuinely characteristics of a cheerful temper, of a brisk mind and of a happy heart. Have courage,
          that is the best advice.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="section">
        <head>§. 2.</head>
        <p xml:id="p2-1">
          The quavers or plain notes in the <ref target="#m-503">sixteenth</ref>, <ref target="#m-550">seventeenth</ref>, and
          <ref target="#m-605">eighteenth</ref> measure indicate by themselves, that something varying might be applied in the right
          hand. How exactly it has to be done should be derived from the previous material. For this work is disposed in such a way, that
          everything in the piece has either already been there or it will soon appear, which possibly extraodinary thing has to be done. Thus, everything
          coheres so naturally and differs so little from the main theme, that it is rather easy to find the right meaning. In order
          not to be accused once more of speaking in riddles, this little may give instructions for further reflection:
        </p>
        <notatedMusic>
          <ptr target="music-example1.xml" />
        </notatedMusic>
        <p xml:id="p2-2">
          It hopefully has been said often enough that the left hand has to play the figures and chords when playing this figuration.
          I would often have liked to put it down in the bass just as it should be, if only the notes could be printed together
          as they can be written or engraved on copper.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3" type="section">
        <head>§. 3.</head>
        <p xml:id="p3-1">
          Another instance occurs in the <ref target="#m-781">23rd measure</ref>, so that the previous can be taken for advice.
          In the <ref target="#m-802">24th measure</ref> thirds can be played, together with a full-voice texture.
          In the <ref target="#m-863">25th measure</ref> it is done as before.
          The <ref target="#m-997">29th</ref>, <ref target="#m-1027">30th</ref> and <ref target="#m-1069">31st measure</ref> allow for an
          alternation as the right hand imitates the left and modulates on the quarter notes according to the motive. If it seems obscure,
          look at this line:<note type="editorial">Here, Mattheson mistakenly shifted the bar line for a quarter note.</note>
          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example2.xml" />
          </notatedMusic>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4" type="section">
        <head>§. 4.</head>
        <p xml:id="p4-1">
          In the <ref target="#m-1123">33rd</ref> measure it might not sound bad if the chords, including sixths and fifths,
          were played and syncopated a little more than usual, in about the following manner:
          <note type="editorial">In the following example, Mattheson
          changed the left-hand-motive into a dactylic rhythm.</note>
        </p>
        <notatedMusic>
          <ptr target="music-example3.xml" />
        </notatedMusic>
        <p xml:id="p4-2">
          There is nothing more to remember or to facilitate in this piece.
        </p>
      </div>



      <note type="on-key-signature">
        Johann Mattheson, <hi rendition="#i">Das Neu-ero&#x0364;ffnete Orchester</hi>, Hamburg 1713: Wenn man nun [...] D.MOLL, [...] wol untersuchet / [...] so wird man befinden / daß er etwas DEVOTES, ruhiges / dabey auch etwas grosses / angenehmes und zufriedenes enthalte; dannenhero derselbe in Kirchen=Sachen die Andacht / in COMMUNI VITA [im weltlichen Leben] aber die Gemu&#x0364;ths=Ruhe zu befo&#x0364;rdern CAPABLE [in der Lage] sey; wiewohl solches alles nichts hindert / daß man nicht auch was ergetzliches / doch nicht sonderlich hu&#x0364;pfendes / sondern fliessendes / mit SUCCES [Erfolg] aus diesem Tohne setzen ko&#x0364;nne [...] zum Heroischen oder Helden=Gedichte ist er am bequemesten. Denn er hat nebst der Hurtigkeit [S. 237] eine wunderbare GRAVIta&#x0364;t [Wu&#x0364;rde] etc. [...] ARISTOTELES nennet ihn: ernsthafft und besta&#x0364;ndig. [...]
      </note>

      <note type="on-meter">
        Johann Mattheson, <hi rendition="#i">Das Neu-ero&#x0364;ffnete Orchester</hi>, Hamburg 1713, S. 79: C. Bedeutet,
        daß die Mensur 4. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Subdivisiones</foreign> und vier viertel habe, deren zwey im Nieder- und zwey im Aufschlage gehen.
        Ihr gebrauch ist groß in Arien, Allemanden, Bouréen etc. und fast durchgehends die gewo&#x0364;hnliche, deswegen sie auch der schlechte Tact genannt wird.
      </note>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
